<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <glossary>  <term category="general" name="Aerobic">Aerobic exercise is physical exercise that intends to improve the oxygen system. Aerobic means "with oxygen", and refers to the use of oxygen in the body's metabolic or energy generating process. Many types of exercise are aerobic, and by definition are performed at moderate levels of intensity for extended periods of time.</term> <term category="general" name="Anaerobic">Anaerobic exercise is exercise intense enough to trigger anaerobic metabolism. It is used by athletes in non-endurance sports to promote strength; speed and power to build muscle mass. Muscles trained using anaerobic exercise, develop differently compared to aerobic exercise, leading to greater performance in short duration, high intensity activities, which last from mere seconds up to about 2 minutes.</term>
<term category="general" name="Anaerobic threshold">Anaerobic threshold is the point at which your body switches from using oxygen as its primary source of energy to using stored sugar. When you’re in poor physical shape, you hit your anaerobic threshold while exercising at relatively low levels of exercise.</term> <term category="general" name="Brick">Brick session is usually a bike/run combo. This stimulates the bike to run transition - many think it's the toughest part of the race.</term> <term category="general" name="DOMS">Delayed onset muscle soreness, also called muscle fever, is the pain and stiffness felt in muscles several hours to days after unaccustomed or strenuous exercise. The soreness is felt most strongly 24-72 hours after the exercise.</term> <term category="running" name="Fartlek">Fartlek is a form of interval training, which puts stress on the whole aerobic energy system due to the nature of the exercise. The difference between this type of training and continuous training is that the intensity or speed of the exercise varies, meaning that aerobic and anaerobic systems can be put under stress. It differs from traditional interval training in that it's unstructerd; intensity and/or speed can be varied as the athlete wishes. The term Fartlek means "speed play" in Swedish.</term> <term category="general" name="Interval">Interval training is a type of physical training that involves bursts of high intensity work. This high intensity work is alternated with periods of rest or low activity.</term> <term category="general" name="Lactate">Lactate threshold is a useful measure for deciding exercise intensity for training and racing during endurance sports (e.g. long distance running, cycling, rowing, swimming and cross country skiing), but varies between individuals and can be increased during training.</term> <term category="general" name="Overtraining">Overtraining is a physical, behavioural and emotional condition that occurs when the volume and intensity of an individual's experience exceeds their recovery capacity.</term> <term category="general" name="Resistance">Resistance training is any exercise that causes the muscles to contract against an external resistance with the expectation of increases in strength, tone, mass and/or endurance.</term> <term category="running" name="Tempo">Tempo running is one of the most effective ways to improve your ability to cover distance at speed. Tempo pace is usually run at what is called the individual's lactate threshold, which has been determined in laboratory and other tests to be the optimal metabolic rate at which the individual can train. Lactate threshold usually occurs between 85% and 90% of maximum heart rate. At this pace, the body is removing lactic acid as fast as it is being produced, any faster and lactic acid will build up in the individual's system, any slower and the optimal training does not result.</term> <term category="general" name="Warm down">is the term used to describe an easy exercise that will allow the body to gradually transition from an exertional state to a resting or near-resting state. Depending on the intensity of the exercise, cooling down helps remove lactic acid, which can cause cramps and stiffness and allows the heart rate to return to its resting rate.</term> <term category="general" name="Warm up">Generally consists of a gradual increase in intensity in physical activity (pulse raiser), a joint mobility exercise, stretching and a sport related activity.</term> <term category="resistance" name="barbells">The larger weights (for power lifting in a weight training program) that include a long bar with weights added to each end. You need to use both hands to lift a barbell.</term>
<term category="resistance" name="dumbbells">Smaller weights (for a weight training program) that you can lift with one hand.</term>
<term category="general" name="Bioelectrical Impedance Analysis">Bioelectrical Impedance Analysis (BIA): A method of measuring your body fat in which you lie on your back while a signal travels from an electrode on your foot to an electrode on your hand. The slower the signal, the more fat you have.</term>
<term category="health" name="blood pressure">blood pressure: A measurement of how open your blood vessels are. Low numbers mean that your heart doesn’t have to work very hard to pump the blood through your blood vessels.</term>
<term category="health" name="body composition">body composition: How much of your body is composed of fat and how much is composed of everything else. Your body composition is also called your body-fat percentage.</term>
<term category="health" name="BMI">Body Mass Index: A way of relating your height and weight to estimate how fat you are. You can use a simple formula to determine your BMI.</term>
<term category="general" name="BOSU">A domed, flexible apparatus that helps to improve balance and can be used in a step aerobics exercise routine. BOSU is an acronym for Both Sides Utilized.</term>
<term category="general" name="Chi">Otherwise known as "life energy," this is the life force that pulses through your body and keeps you vital. Blocked chi can cause sickness or unhappiness.</term>
<term category="general" name="circuit training">A fast-paced class or exercise routine in which you do one exercise for 30 seconds to 5 minutes and then move on to another exercise at the next station. Combines cardio exercise with strength training.</term>
<term category="general" name="Core">The abdomen, obliques, lower back, butt, and so on, that form the midsection. Many forms of exercise focus on strengthening the body's core.</term>
<term category="general" name="core conditioning">A non-aerobic, muscle-toning class, usually focused on core strength.</term>
<term category="general" name="cross-training">A method of varying your workouts to take your fitness to the next level by adding new forms of training to your current routine.</term>
<term category="general" name="elliptical trainer">The hottest trend in cardio machines, which is part stair-climber, part treadmill, part stationary cycle. Your legs travel in an elongated circular movement, and, on some models, you pump arm poles back and forth for an upper-body workout.</term>
<term category="general" name="exercise ball">A large plastic ball that is an excellent tool for doing challenging exercises (with or without weights) that require varying forms of strength and control.</term>
<term category="running" name="fitness walking">A faster and more intense walking technique than casual (lifestyle) walking that burns more calories and helps you lose weight. When you fitness walk, you generally move along at a brisk pace of 3.5 to 4.3 miles an hour, covering a mile in 14 to 17 minutes.</term>
<term category="general" name="flexibility">The range of motion or distance you can move a joint through. Stretching is the key to maintaining your flexibility.</term>
<term category="resistance" name="free weights">Portable weights used in a strength training program.</term>
<term category="swimming" name="freestyle">The traditional type of swimming movement that uses the front crawl.</term>
<term category="general" name="heart rate">The number of times your heart beats per minute.</term>
<term category="general" name="aerobics high-impact">A traditional dance-inspired routine that involves jumping or hopping and moves at a slower pace than low-impact aerobics. High/low combines the two types of routines.</term>
<term category="general" name="interval training">A training technique in which you alternate short, fairly intense spurts of exercise with periods of relatively easy exercise.</term>
<term category="general" name="lifestyle walking">A casual walking technique that is low to moderate intensity and relatively slow paced. Most lifestyle walkers walk an average of 2.5 to 3.5 miles per hour, which means that they walk about 1 mile every 17 to 24 minutes.</term>
<term category="general" name="aerobics low-impact">A traditional dance-inspired routine in which you always have one foot on the floor — you don’t do any jumping or hopping. High/low combines the two types of routines.</term>
<term category="running" name="marathon">An organized 26.2-mile race for runners and walkers.</term>
<term category="general" name="heart rate maximum">The maximum number of times your heart should beat in a minute without dangerously overexerting yourself.</term>
<term category="general" name="meditation">A mental process involving focused attention, or calm awareness, which is also called mindfulness.</term>
<term category="cycling" name="mountain bike">A fat-tire outdoors bicycle with upright handlebars that is built to withstand rough terrain.</term>
<term category="resistance" name="multi-gym">A home gym contraption that looks like a bunch of health-club weight machines welded to each other.</term>
<term category="resistance" name="muscular failure">In a strength training program, the point at which your last repetition with weights is so difficult that you cannot perform another repetition.</term>
<term category="general" name="orthotics">Fitted shoe inserts designed by a podiatrist that correct weight distribution along the foot.</term>
<term category="general" name="periodization">A method of organizing a strength training workout program into several periods, each lasting about four weeks. Each phase has a different emphasis.</term>
<term category="general" name="Pilates">A form of exercise that emphasizes correct form using your body’s core. Pilates is named after its inventor, Joseph Pilates, who invented the technique for injured dancers.</term>
<term category="general" name="plantar fasciitis">An inflammation of the tough fibrous band of tissue that runs the length of the bottom of your foot.</term>
<term category="general" name="Qigong">An element of a T'ai Chi practice that covers many different types of movements that involve using and feeling the body's energy.</term>
<term category="cycling" name="recumbent bike">A type of stationary bike with a bucket seat that provides back support so that you pedal straight out in front of you.</term>
<term category="resistance" name="Rep">repetition: One complete motion of an exercise, often used in reference to strength training.</term>
<term category="health" name="R.I.C.E.">An acronym that stands for Rest, Ice, Compression, and Elevation — common treatment methods prescribed for runners with training injuries.</term>
<term category="cycling" name="road bike">The traditional type of outdoor bicycle with curved handlebars that is built for speed.</term>
<term category="general" name="rolling stair climber">A cardiovascular machine that resembles a section of a department-store escalator. A set of stairs rotates in a circle so that you climb continuously, but never getting anywhere.</term>
<term category="general"  name="rowing machine">A cardiovascular machine that increases stamina, upper body endurance, strength, and flexibility by mimicking a rowing motion. Also called a rower.</term>
<term category="resistance" name="Set">A group of consecutive repetitions in a strength training program.</term>
<term category="cycling" name="Spinning">A popular group studio cycling program invented by ultra-distance cyclist Johnny G. and licensed by Schwinn, which manufactures the bikes used in these classes.</term>
<term category="general" name="stair-climber">A cardiovascular machine that has two foot plates you pump up and down to mimic the action of climbing stairs. Also called a stepper.</term>
<term category="general" name="stationary bike">A cardiovascular machine that comes in two styles: upright bikes and recumbent bikes.</term>
<term category="general" name="aerobics step">A choreographed routine of stepping up and down on a rectangular, square, or circular platform.</term>
<term category="general" name="strength training">A type of workout that uses any combination of weight machines and free weights (dumbbells and barbells) to build muscle strength.</term>
<term category="running" name="stride frequency">The number of strides that a runner takes over a certain time period.</term>
<term category="general" name="studio cycling">Group exercise classes that are taught on stationary bicycles.</term>
<term category="general" name="T'ai Chi">An ancient martial art focusing on smooth, slow movements that cultivate inward focus and free energy flow. T'ai Chi is properly pronounced tie-jee.</term>
<term category="general" name="target heart-rate zone">A range that is between 50 percent and 85 percent of your maximum heart rate that can tell you what heart rate to aim for during a workout.</term>
<term category="running" name="treadmill">A popular choice for a cardiovascular machine in a home gym if you enjoy fitness walking and jogging (or running).</term>
<term category="cycling" name="upright bike">The traditional kind of stationary bike, which resembles a regular bicycle.</term>
<term category="running" name="walk-run">A workout in which you alternate walking and running. By sprinkling running intervals throughout your walking workout, you can spike up exercise intensity and burn more calories.</term>
<term category="general" name="aerobics water">Aerobics classes that do traditional workouts in waist- to neck-high water in a swimming pool. The resistance of the water makes the workout feel far more intense, while the water cushions you from the impact.</term>
<term category="resistance" name="weight machines">Stationary equipment mostly found at gyms that are easy to use and help you to safely and quickly advance through a strength-training workout.</term>
<term category="general" name="weight-bearing exercise">A type of exercise in which your skeleton is supporting any sort of weight, as it does when you walk, run, or lift weights.</term>
<term category="general" name="Wushu">The “martial art” or traditional self-defense activities practiced with or without weapons (includes T'ai Chi).</term>
<term category="general" name="yin and yang">The terms for opposites that are opposing yet complementary. A concept used throughout all of T’ai Chi and Qigong.</term>
<term category="general" name="yoga">A series of poses (known as asanas) that you hold from a few seconds to several minutes. The moves — a blend of strength, flexibility, and body-awareness exercises — are intended to promote the union of the mind, body, and spirit.</term>
<term category="general" name="10-K pace">10-K pace, when used in a workout to describe how fast to run, is simply the pace of a runner's last 10-K race. "10-K pace" is therefore different for every runner; for a 62-minute 10-K runner, "10-K pace" is 10 minutes per mile; for 31:00, it's 5 minutes per mile; for Paul Tergat, it's 4:16 per mile.</term>
<term category="general" name="5-K/8-K/10-K">K is for kilometers, 1,000 meters. A 5-K is equal to 3.1 miles; 8-K is 4.96 miles; 10-K is equal to 6.2 miles.</term>
<term category="general" name="400 meters">Equivalent to a quarter mile or 1 lap around a standard track.</term>
<term category="general" name="800 meters">Equivalent to a half-mile or 2 laps around a standard track.</term>
<term category="general" name="AIMS">Association of International Marathons and Road Races. More information can be found at www.aims-association.org.</term>
<term category="general" name="ASOIF">Association of Summer Olympic International Federations. More information can be found at www.asoif.com.</term>
<term category="general" name="aerobic">Used to refer to running or other exercise at an intensity that's sufficiently easy for your respiratory and cardiovascular systems to deliver all or most of the oxygen required by your muscles, and slow enough that lactic acid doesn't appreciably build up in your muscles. Generally, you can sustain a slow aerobic pace for long periods of time, provided you have the endurance to go long distances.10-K pace  10-K pace, when used in a workout to describe how fast to run, is simply the pace of a runner's last 10-K race. "10-K pace" is therefore different for every runner; for a 62-minute 10-K runner, "10-K pace" is 10 minutes per mile; for 31:00, it's 5 minutes per mile; for Paul Tergat, it's 4:16 per mile.</term>
<term category="general" name="5-K/8-K/10-K">K is for kilometers, 1,000 meters. A 5-K is equal to 3.1 miles; 8-K is 4.96 miles; 10-K is equal to 6.2 miles.</term>
<term category="general" name="400 meters">Equivalent to a quarter mile or 1 lap around a standard track.</term>
<term category="general" name="800 meters">Equivalent to a half-mile or 2 laps around a standard track.</term>
<term category="general" name="AIMS">Association of International Marathons and Road Races. More information can be found at www.aims-association.org.</term>
<term category="general" name="ASOIF">Association of Summer Olympic International Federations. More information can be found at www.asoif.com.</term>
<term category="general" name="aerobic">Used to refer to running or other exercise at an intensity that's sufficiently easy for your respiratory and cardiovascular systems to deliver all or most of the oxygen required by your muscles, and slow enough that lactic acid doesn't appreciably build up in your muscles. Generally, you can sustain a slow aerobic pace for long periods of time, provided you have the endurance to go long distances.</term>
<term category="general" name="anaerobic">Used to refer to running or other exercise at an intensity that makes it impossible for your respiratory and cardiovascular systems to deliver all or most of the oxygen required by your muscles, and fast enough that lactic acid begins to build up in your muscles, thus producing a tired, heavy feeling. The pace associated with anaerobic running cannot be sustained very long.</term>
<term category="general" name="anaerobic threshold (AT)">The transition phase between aerobic and anaerobic running. Good training will increase AT by teaching the muscles to use oxygen more efficiently, so that less lactic acid is produced. Also known as "lactate threshold."</term>
<term category="general" name="bonk">See "hitting the wall."</term>
<term category="general" name="chip time">A technology for sensing and recording the finishing times of all the runners in a race. It's much more accurate and can easily deal with the old problem of many runners finishing nearly at once in a big, crowded race. The "chip" is a tiny electronic chip that's programmed with your specific runner identification. You attach the chip to your shoe laces. It sends a signal to an electronic reading device--often hidden under a strip of carpet-- when you cross the start line and again when you cross the finish line. No human observation is necessary. Your exact time is recorded automatically. Usually you are asked to turn the chip back in to the race organizers.</term>
<term category="general" name="clydesdale">A weight-challenged runner. To find out more about Clydesdale running and racing, try this web site: http://www.clydesdale.org/.</term>
<term category="general" name="cool-down">Slow running or jogging done after a workout or competition to loosen muscles and rid the body of lactic acid.</term>
<term category="general" name="CR">Course record.</term>
<term category="general" name="cushioning (or shock absorption)">The ability of a shoe to absorb the impact of footstrike.</term>
<term category="general" name="DNF">Did not finish.</term>
<term category="general" name="DNS">Did not start.</term>
<term category="general" name="DOMS">Delayed onset muscle soreness. This type of muscle soreness normally peaks about 48 hours after a particularly intense or long run.</term>
<term category="general" name="elite runner">An athlete who has reached the highest level in his/her sport.</term>
<term category="general" name="fartlek">Swedish for "speed play;" variable pace running; a mixture of slow running, running at a moderate pace and short, fast bursts. Fartlek training is a "creative way" to increase speed and endurance.</term>
<term category="general" name="'hitting the wall'">The dreaded point (and awful feeling similar to what your body would feel like if you ran into a wall) during a race when your muscle glycogen stores become depleted and a feeling of fatigue engulfs you.</term>
<term category="general" name="IAAF">International Amateur Athletic Federation. More information can be found at www.iaaf.org.</term>
<term category="general" name="IOC">International Olympic Committee. More information can be found at www.olympic.org.</term>
<term category="general" name="intervals">Training in which short, fast "repeats" or "repetitions" often 200 to 800 meters, are alternated with slow "intervals" of jogging for recovery; usually based on a rigid format such as "six times 400 meters fast [these are the repeats] with 400-meter recovery jogs [the intervals]," interval training builds speed and endurance.</term>
<term category="general" name="junior">According to the IAAF, a junior is any athlete who is under 20 on December 31 of that year. For example, an athlete whose birthday is November 12, 1979 will be a junior in 1998 but not in 1999.</term>
<term category="general" name="junk miles">Runs at an easy pace inserted into a program in order to reach a weekly or monthly mileage total rather than for any specific benefit. Despite the name, "junk miles" often serve as recovery from harder workouts. The value of "junk miles" is still hotly debated among training theorists.</term>
<term category="general" name="lactic acid">A substance which forms in the muscles as a result of the incomplete breakdown of glucose. Lactic acid is associated with muscle fatigue and sore muscles.</term>
<term category="general" name="lactate threshold">  See "anaerobic threshold." </term>
<term category="general" name="last">  A shaped piece of wood or metal on which the shoe is built. The shape of the last determines the shape of the shoe. Shoes are made in three basic shapes: straight, curved and semi-curved, but all three shapes vary from company to company as each company has its own lasts.</term>
<term category="general" name="lateral">  Refers to the outer edge of a shoe.</term>
<term category="general" name="LSD">  NOT the hallucinogen. LSD is an abbreviation for "Long, Slow Distance," which refers to the practice of running longer distances at an "easy" pace rather than shorter ones to exhaustion. The slower pace allows the runner to go longer and, therefore (supposedly), gain more fitness.</term>
<term category="general" name="Marathon">  26.2 miles; According to legend, in 490 B.C., a Greek soldier name Philippides ran the distance from the site of the battle of Marathon to Athens, where he died after the Greek victory over the Persians.</term>
<term category="general" name="Master">  An athlete 40 years of age or older is designated a "master" in the U.S. Many other countries use the term "veteran." </term>
<term category="general" name="maximum heart rate">  The highest heart-rate reached during a specified period of time.</term>
<term category="general" name="medial">  Referring to the inner side (or arch side) of a shoe.</term>
<term category="general" name="'metric mile'">  1500m, the international racing distance closest to the imperial mile.</term>
<term category="general" name="midsole">  The area of the shoe between the upper and outsole that's primarily responsible for the shoe's cushioning. Most midsoles are made of foams: either EVA (ethylene vinyl acetate) or polyurethane. EVA is lighter and more flexible than polyurethane, but it also breaks down more quickly. Many midsoles also have additional cushioning elements such as air, gel and various embedded plastic units.</term>
<term category="general" name="mile">  1609 meters, 5280 feet, or 1760 yards. Note: 1600m is not a mile.</term>
<term category="general" name="motion control">  The ability of a shoe to limit overpronation.</term>
<term category="general" name="negative splits">  Running the second half of a race faster than the first half.</term>
<term category="general" name="NR">  National record.</term>
<term category="general" name="outsole">  The material, usually made of hard carbon rubber, on the bottom of most running shoes; the layer of the shoe that contacts the ground.</term>
<term category="general" name="overpronation">The excessive inward roll of the foot before toe-off. Overpronation is believed to be the cause of many running injuries.</term>
<term category="general" name="pick-ups">Accelerations done during a run, normally done in shorter durations than fartleks. Pick-ups are simply another way to spice up what would otherwise be an easy-run day.</term>
<term category="general" name="plyometrics">Bounding exercises; any jumping exercise in which landing followed by a jump occurs.</term>
<term category="general" name="post (or medial post)">Firmer density of midsole material added to the inner side of the shoe. A post is designed to reduce overpronation.</term>
<term category="general" name="prep">In the U.S., a high school athlete. From the term "preparatory school," a school for preparing for college. Slightly different from the IAAF definition of "Junior." </term>
<term category="general" name="pronation">Pronation begins immediately after the heel contacts the ground. It is a normal and necessary motion for walking or running. Pronation is the distinctive, inward roll of the foot as the arch collapses.</term>
<term category="general" name="PR/PB">Personal record/personal best.</term>
<term category="general" name="RRCA">Road Runners Club of America. More information can be found at www.rrca.org.</term>
<term category="general" name="repeats">See "intervals." </term>
<term category="general" name="ride">The ability of a shoe to provide a smooth transfer of a runner's weight from heel-strike to toe-off. Ride is a largely subjective quality, but shoe wearers know it when a shoe has or lacks a good ride.</term>
<term category="general" name="runner's high">A feeling, usually unexpected, of exhilaration and well-being directly associated with vigorous running; apparently related to the secretion of endorphins.</term>
<term category="general" name="running economy">Refers to how much oxygen you use when you run. When you improve your economy, you are able to run at a smaller percentage of max VO2 (your maximum rate of oxygen utilization).</term>
<term category="general" name="splits">Refers to your times at mile markers or other pre-planned checkpoints along the way to the finish line.</term>
<term category="general" name="stability">The ability of a shoe to resist excessive foot motion </term>
<term category="general" name="strides">Short, fast, but controlled runs of 50 to 150 meters. Strides, which are used both in training and to warm up before a race, build speed and efficiency.</term>
<term category="general" name="supination">The opposite of pronation. It's an outward rolling of the forefoot that naturally occurs during the stride cycle at toe-off. Oversupination occurs when the foot remains on its outside edge after heel strike instead of pronating. A true oversupinating foot underpronates or does not pronate at all, so it doesn't absorb shock well. It is a rare condition occurring in less than 1 percent of the running population.</term>
<term category="general" name="taper">Runners usually cut back mileage (or taper) one day to three weeks (depending on race distance) before a big race. Tapering helps muscles rest so that they are ready for peak performance on race day.</term>
<term category="general" name="target heart rate">A range of heart rate reached during aerobic training, which enables an athlete to gain maximum benefit.</term>
<term category="general" name="tempo runs">Sustained effort training runs, usually 20 to 30 minutes in length, at 10 to 15 seconds per mile slower than 10-K race pace. Another way to gauge the pace of tempo runs: a pace about midway between short-interval training speed and your easy running pace.</term>
<term category="general" name="threshold runs">Runs of 5 to 20 minutes at a pace just a little slower than your 10-K racing pace; Threshold pace is roughly equivalent to what exercise physiologists call "lactate threshold," or the point at which your muscles start fatiguing at a rapid rate. Running at or near lactate threshold is believed to raise your lactate threshold, which should allow you to run faster in the future.</term>
<term category="general" name="toebox">The front portion of a shoe's upper. A wide toebox allows plenty of room for the toes to spread.</term>
<term category="general" name="underpronator">Underpronation is less common than overpronation. The shoes of underpronators show outsole wear on the lateral (outer) side not just at the heel but all the way up to the forefoot. Typically, underpronators tend to break down the heel counters of their shoes on the lateral side.</term>
<term category="general" name="upper">The leather or mesh material that encloses the foot.</term>
<term category="general" name="USATF">USA Track and Field. More information can be found at www.usatf.org.</term>
<term category="general" name="USOC">United States Olympic Committee. More information can be found at www.usoc.org.</term>
<term category="general" name="veteran">International term similar to "master" in the U.S. According to the IAAF, men become "veterans" on their 40th birthday; women, on their 35th birthday.</term>
<term category="general" name="VO2Max (maximal oxygen consumption)">The maximal amount of oxygen that a person can extract from the atmosphere and then transport and use in the body's tissues.</term>
<term category="general" name="warm-up">Five to twenty minutes of easy jogging/walking before a race or a workout. The point of a warm-up is to raise one's heart rate so the body (and its muscles) are looser before a tough workout begins.</term>
<term category="general" name="'world best'">A recorded best time for an event in which formal world records are not kept. For instance, the fastest time at 150m, a non-standard distance, is a "world best" rather than a "world record." Similar distinctions are made for road races which do not meet certain standards, such as races with excessive amounts of downhill.</term>
<term category="general" name="anaerobic">Used to refer to running or other exercise at an intensity that makes it impossible for your respiratory and cardiovascular systems to deliver all or most of the oxygen required by your muscles, and fast enough that lactic acid begins to build up in your muscles, thus producing a tired, heavy feeling. The pace associated with anaerobic running cannot be sustained very long.</term>
<term category="general" name="anaerobic threshold (AT)">The transition phase between aerobic and anaerobic running. Good training will increase AT by teaching the muscles to use oxygen more efficiently, so that less lactic acid is produced. Also known as "lactate threshold."</term>
<term category="general" name="bonk">See "hitting the wall."</term>
<term category="general" name="chip time">A technology for sensing and recording the finishing times of all the runners in a race. It's much more accurate and can easily deal with the old problem of many runners finishing nearly at once in a big, crowded race. The "chip" is a tiny electronic chip that's programmed with your specific runner identification. You attach the chip to your shoe laces. It sends a signal to an electronic reading device--often hidden under a strip of carpet-- when you cross the start line and again when you cross the finish line. No human observation is necessary. Your exact time is recorded automatically. Usually you are asked to turn the chip back in to the race organizers.</term>
<term category="general" name="clydesdale">A weight-challenged runner. To find out more about Clydesdale running and racing, try this web site: http://www.clydesdale.org/.</term>
<term category="general" name="cool-down">Slow running or jogging done after a workout or competition to loosen muscles and rid the body of lactic acid.</term>
<term category="general" name="CR">Course record.</term>
<term category="general" name="cushioning (or shock absorption)">The ability of a shoe to absorb the impact of footstrike.</term>
<term category="general" name="DNF">Did not finish.</term>
<term category="general" name="DNS">Did not start.</term>
<term category="general" name="DOMS">Delayed onset muscle soreness. This type of muscle soreness normally peaks about 48 hours after a particularly intense or long run.</term>
<term category="general" name="elite runner">An athlete who has reached the highest level in his/her sport.</term>
<term category="general" name="fartlek">Swedish for "speed play;" variable pace running; a mixture of slow running, running at a moderate pace and short, fast bursts. Fartlek training is a "creative way" to increase speed and endurance.</term>
<term category="general" name="'hitting the wall'">The dreaded point (and awful feeling similar to what your body would feel like if you ran into a wall) during a race when your muscle glycogen stores become depleted and a feeling of fatigue engulfs you.</term>
<term category="general" name="IAAF">International Amateur Athletic Federation. More information can be found at www.iaaf.org.</term>
<term category="general" name="IOC">International Olympic Committee. More information can be found at www.olympic.org.</term>
<term category="general" name="intervals">Training in which short, fast "repeats" or "repetitions" often 200 to 800 meters, are alternated with slow "intervals" of jogging for recovery; usually based on a rigid format such as "six times 400 meters fast [these are the repeats] with 400-meter recovery jogs [the intervals]," interval training builds speed and endurance.</term>
<term category="general" name="junior">According to the IAAF, a junior is any athlete who is under 20 on December 31 of that year. For example, an athlete whose birthday is November 12, 1979 will be a junior in 1998 but not in 1999.</term>
<term category="general" name="junk miles">Runs at an easy pace inserted into a program in order to reach a weekly or monthly mileage total rather than for any specific benefit. Despite the name, "junk miles" often serve as recovery from harder workouts. The value of "junk miles" is still hotly debated among training theorists.</term>
<term category="general" name="lactic acid">A substance which forms in the muscles as a result of the incomplete breakdown of glucose. Lactic acid is associated with muscle fatigue and sore muscles.</term>
<term category="general" name="lactate threshold">See "anaerobic threshold." </term>
<term category="general" name="last">A shaped piece of wood or metal on which the shoe is built. The shape of the last determines the shape of the shoe. Shoes are made in three basic shapes: straight, curved and semi-curved, but all three shapes vary from company to company as each company has its own lasts.</term>
<term category="general" name="lateral">Refers to the outer edge of a shoe.</term>
<term category="general" name="LSD">NOT the hallucinogen. LSD is an abbreviation for "Long, Slow Distance," which refers to the practice of running longer distances at an "easy" pace rather than shorter ones to exhaustion. The slower pace allows the runner to go longer and, therefore (supposedly), gain more fitness.</term>
<term category="general" name="Marathon">26.2 miles; According to legend, in 490 B.C., a Greek soldier name Philippides ran the distance from the site of the battle of Marathon to Athens, where he died after the Greek victory over the Persians.</term>
<term category="general" name="Master">An athlete 40 years of age or older is designated a "master" in the U.S. Many other countries use the term "veteran." </term>
<term category="general" name="maximum heart rate">The highest heart-rate reached during a specified period of time.</term>
<term category="general" name="medial">Referring to the inner side (or arch side) of a shoe.</term>
<term category="general" name="'metric mile'">1500m, the international racing distance closest to the imperial mile.</term>
<term category="general" name="midsole">The area of the shoe between the upper and outsole that's primarily responsible for the shoe's cushioning. Most midsoles are made of foams: either EVA (ethylene vinyl acetate) or polyurethane. EVA is lighter and more flexible than polyurethane, but it also breaks down more quickly. Many midsoles also have additional cushioning elements such as air, gel and various embedded plastic units.</term>
<term category="general" name="mile">1609 meters, 5280 feet, or 1760 yards. Note: 1600m is not a mile.</term>
<term category="general" name="motion control">The ability of a shoe to limit overpronation.</term>
<term category="general" name="negative splits">Running the second half of a race faster than the first half.</term>
<term category="general" name="outsole">The material, usually made of hard carbon rubber, on the bottom of most running shoes; the layer of the shoe that contacts the ground.</term>
<term category="general" name="overpronation">The excessive inward roll of the foot before toe-off. Overpronation is believed to be the cause of many running injuries.</term>
<term category="general" name="pick-ups">Accelerations done during a run, normally done in shorter durations than fartleks. Pick-ups are simply another way to spice up what would otherwise be an easy-run day.</term>
<term category="general" name="plyometrics">Bounding exercises; any jumping exercise in which landing followed by a jump occurs.</term>
<term category="general" name="post (or medial post)">Firmer density of midsole material added to the inner side of the shoe. A post is designed to reduce overpronation.</term>
<term category="general" name="prep">In the U.S., a high school athlete. From the term "preparatory school," a school for preparing for college. Slightly different from the IAAF definition of "Junior." </term>
<term category="general" name="pronation">Pronation begins immediately after the heel contacts the ground. It is a normal and necessary motion for walking or running. Pronation is the distinctive, inward roll of the foot as the arch collapses.</term>
<term category="general" name="PR/PB">Personal record/personal best.</term>
<term category="general" name="RRCA">Road Runners Club of America. More information can be found at www.rrca.org.</term>
<term category="general" name="repeats">See "intervals." </term>
<term category="general" name="ride">The ability of a shoe to provide a smooth transfer of a runner's weight from heel-strike to toe-off. Ride is a largely subjective quality, but shoe wearers know it when a shoe has or lacks a good ride.</term>
<term category="general" name="runner's high">A feeling, usually unexpected, of exhilaration and well-being directly associated with vigorous running; apparently related to the secretion of endorphins.</term>
<term category="general" name="running economy">Refers to how much oxygen you use when you run. When you improve your economy, you are able to run at a smaller percentage of max VO2 (your maximum rate of oxygen utilization).</term>
<term category="general" name="splits">Refers to your times at mile markers or other pre-planned checkpoints along the way to the finish line.</term>
<term category="general" name="stability">The ability of a shoe to resist excessive foot motion </term>
<term category="general" name="strides">Short, fast, but controlled runs of 50 to 150 meters. Strides, which are used both in training and to warm up before a race, build speed and efficiency.</term>
<term category="general" name="supination">The opposite of pronation. It's an outward rolling of the forefoot that naturally occurs during the stride cycle at toe-off. Oversupination occurs when the foot remains on its outside edge after heel strike instead of pronating. A true oversupinating foot underpronates or does not pronate at all, so it doesn't absorb shock well. It is a rare condition occurring in less than 1 percent of the running population.</term>
<term category="general" name="taper">Runners usually cut back mileage (or taper) one day to three weeks (depending on race distance) before a big race. Tapering helps muscles rest so that they are ready for peak performance on race day.</term>
<term category="general" name="target heart rate">A range of heart rate reached during aerobic training, which enables an athlete to gain maximum benefit.</term>
<term category="general" name="tempo runs">Sustained effort training runs, usually 20 to 30 minutes in length, at 10 to 15 seconds per mile slower than 10-K race pace. Another way to gauge the pace of tempo runs: a pace about midway between short-interval training speed and your easy running pace.</term>
<term category="general" name="threshold runs">Runs of 5 to 20 minutes at a pace just a little slower than your 10-K racing pace; Threshold pace is roughly equivalent to what exercise physiologists call "lactate threshold," or the point at which your muscles start fatiguing at a rapid rate. Running at or near lactate threshold is believed to raise your lactate threshold, which should allow you to run faster in the future.</term>
<term category="general" name="toebox">The front portion of a shoe's upper. A wide toebox allows plenty of room for the toes to spread.</term>
<term category="general" name="underpronator">Underpronation is less common than overpronation. The shoes of underpronators show outsole wear on the lateral (outer) side not just at the heel but all the way up to the forefoot. Typically, underpronators tend to break down the heel counters of their shoes on the lateral side.</term>
<term category="general" name="">The leather or mesh material that encloses the foot.</term>
<term category="general" name="USATF">USA Track and Field. More information can be found at www.usatf.org.</term>
<term category="general" name="USOC">United States Olympic Committee. More information can be found at www.usoc.org.</term>
<term category="general" name="veteran">International term similar to "master" in the U.S. According to the IAAF, men become "veterans" on their 40th birthday; women, on their 35th birthday.</term>
<term category="general" name="VO2Max (maximal oxygen consumption)">The maximal amount of oxygen that a person can extract from the atmosphere and then transport and use in the body's tissues.</term>
<term category="general" name="wall">See "hitting the wall."</term>
<term category="general" name="warm-up">Five to twenty minutes of easy jogging/walking before a race or a workout. The point of a warm-up is to raise one's heart rate so the body (and its muscles) are looser before a tough workout begins.</term>
<term category="general" name="'world best'">A recorded best time for an event in which formal world records are not kept. For instance, the fastest time at 150m, a non-standard distance, is a "world best" rather than a "world record." Similar distinctions are made for road races which do not meet certain standards, such as races with excessive amounts of downhill.</term>
<term category="general" name="WR">World record.</term>
<term category="general" name="">xxxxx</term>
<term category="general" name="">xxxxx</term>
<term category="general" name="">xxxxx</term>
<term category="general" name="">xxxxx</term>
<term category="general" name="">xxxxx</term>
<term category="general" name="">xxxxx</term>
<term category="general" name="">xxxxx</term>
<term category="general" name="">xxxxx</term>
<term category="general" name="">xxxxx</term>
<term category="general" name="">xxxxx</term>
<term category="general" name="">xxxxx</term>
<term category="general" name="">xxxxx</term>
<term category="general" name="">xxxxx</term>
<term category="general" name="">xxxxx</term>
<term category="general" name="">xxxxx</term>
<term category="general" name="">xxxxx</term>
<term category="general" name="">xxxxx</term>
<term category="general" name="">xxxxx</term>
<term category="general" name="">xxxxx</term>
<term category="general" name="">xxxxx</term>
</glossary>
